Guide to the Luther Rice Papers, 1812-1832 MS0260.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Luther Rice papers
1812-1832
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Luther Rice
MS0260.UA
4 Linear Feet
Luther Rice (1783-1836) is regarded as the founder of Columbian College, now The George Washington University. Collection include correspondence financial ledgers, log books. His papers include promissory notes, financial documents, college building appeal, Baptist Documents, notebooks, diaries and other records. The collection covers the twenty year period between 1812 and 1832.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Provenance of this collection not known.
Historical or Biographical Note
Luther Rice (1783-1836) is regarded as the founder of Columbian College, now The George Washington University. Rice was born in Nothborough Massachusetts in 1783 and died in Edgefield district, South Carolina in 1836. Rice entered Williams College in 1807 and there developed a strong interest in foreign missions.
He was ordained as a Congregational minister in Salem, Massachusetts in 1812. In 1813 and after a missionary journey to India, he went to Boston. Having difficulties with policy within the Congregational Church he turned to the Baptists, as had many of his fellow missionaries.
With his missionary zeal he turned to the cause of ministerial education. Mainly through his efforts, fund-raising and personal influence he established, along with five other Baptist missionaries, the Columbian College in the District of Columbia. For several years he served Columbian College as its agent and treasurer.
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include correspondence financial ledgers, log books. His papers include promissory notes, financial documents, college building appeal, Baptist Documents, notebooks, diaries and other records. The collection covers the twenty year period between 1812 and 1832.
Baptists; Washington (D.C.); Diaries; Promissory notes; Fund raising; Columbian College in the District of Columbia; George Washington University; George Washington University--History; Luther Rice
- Outgoing Correspondence, 1815-1818 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Outgoing Correspondence, 1821-1825 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Outgoing Correspondence, 1826-1827 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Outgoing Correspondence, 1828-1829 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Outgoing Correspondence, 1830-1831 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Outgoing Correspondence, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Outgoing Correspondence, 1834-1835 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Outgoing Correspondence, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Outgoing Correspondence n.d., 1824-1826 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Outgoing Correspondence, 1827-1836 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Papers: Promissory Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Papers: Financial Documents, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Papers: College Building Appeal, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Papers: Baptist Documents, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Papers, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Journal of Luther Rice, 1815-20, 1815-1820 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Journal of Luther Rice, 1819-26, 1819-1826 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  General note
  Text with item: "This so-called 'Journal' of Luther Rice, 1819-26, was actually more of an account book for financial activities relating to the college. Rice was a slovenly bookkeeper and his disorganization led to severe monetary problems. He was blamed for the financial crisis of the college in 1826 and a move was made to investigate his operations. Their report was that Rice was clear of any immoral conduct but was a 'very loose accountant...with very imperfect talents for the disboursement of the money.'"
- Journal of Luther Rice, 1826, 01/1826-05/1826 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Appears to be an account of finances for Columbian College.
- Journal 1803-7 from the American Baptist Historical Society, Journal 1812 [bound photocopies], 1803-1812 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Luther Rice Financial Record Book, 1819-20. [bound photocopies], 1819-1820 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Luther Rice letter accounts, 1815. Journal 1816-9. Cash Book 1820. [bound photocopies], 1815-1820 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Luther Rice classroom lecture note book, account book, July 1810, journal 1819 [bound photocopies], 1810-1819 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Journal and account book [bound photocopies], 1815-1817 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- A register of letters received and sent by Luther Rice, 1823-1827 (Box 4, Folder 6)